<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Encoding of songtexts from Tools Album "Lateralus" and their
               interpretation</title>
            <editor>Martin Kroissenbrunner</editor>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>57 KB</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>The document was created for learning purposes, it is not intended for
               publication!</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>The source of the lyrics is the website
                  "<ref>https://toolband.com/releases/lateralus/</ref>". That of the interpretation
               is "<ref>https://genius.com/Tool-lateralus-lyrics</ref>"</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>The album "Lateralus" by the band "Tool" is at the center of this project. The aim of
               the final project in the course "X-Technologien I", is to encode the lyrics as well
               as interpretations of this album.</p>
         </projectDesc>
         <samplingDecl>
            <p>The following text consists of the lyrics and interpretations of these. In order to
               work with the correct lyrics, the editor decided to get them from the band's official
               website. Regarding the interpretations, the site "genius.com" was used. The site
               allows users to provide annotations and interpretation to song lyrics, news stories,
               sources, poetry, and documents. However, the interpretations were not adopted
               one-to-one, but summarized as well as expanded by the editor´s point of view. The
               structuring of the song texts in verse, chorus, etc. was also based on
               "genius.com".</p>
         </samplingDecl>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p/>
            <correction>
               <p>Obvious errors were marked as <gi>sic</gi>, however, a corrected version is not
                  offered.</p>
            </correction>
            <p>The structure of the text looks like this: the <gi>div</gi>-elements contain the
               total of 9 songs. The sections of the songs (verse, refrain, pre-chorus, etc.) are in
               turn structured with <gi>lg</gi> elements. The <gi>l</gi> elements contain the
               individual lines. The <gi>note</gi> elements refer either to individual lines or to
               entire sections and contain the interpretations. Since the metric scheme of the song
               "Lateralus" is important for the interpretation of the lyrics the <gi>met</gi>-
               attribute is used here as an exception. Also persons, books or terms mentioned in the
               lyrics are normalized and/or described in the <gi>standOff</gi>-Element. The focus is
               on the lyrics, so musical features like key, tempo or tact won´t be mentioned. The
               album consists of thirteen songs. If you look at the numbering, you will notice that
               some songs are missing. That´s because the second, fourth and twelveth songs are
               instrumental. The thirteenth song includes talking, that is from a radio call-in show
               and therefore no work of the band.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
      </encodingDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <standOff>
      <listPerson>
         <person xml:id="NaHa">
            <persName>
               <forename>Nathaniel</forename>
               <surname>Hawthorne</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth>1804</birth>
            <death>1864</death>
            <idno type="VIAF">44435463</idno>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="MaJaKe">
            <persName>
               <forename>Maynard</forename>
               <forename>James</forename>
               <surname>Keenan</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth>1964</birth>
            <idno type="VIAF">481149294285080521418</idno>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="JeChNa">
            <persName>
               <forename>Jesus</forename>
               <forename>Christus</forename>
               <nameLink>von</nameLink>
               <placeName>Nazareth</placeName>
            </persName>
            <birth>4 v. Chr.</birth>
            <death>29 n. Chr</death>
            <idno type="VIAF">38323081</idno>
         </person>
         <person xml:id="CaJu">
            <persName>
               <forename>Carl</forename>
               <forename>Gustav</forename>
               <surname>Jung</surname>
            </persName>
            <birth>1875</birth>
            <death>1961</death>
            <idno type="VIAF">88819182</idno>
         </person>
      </listPerson>
      <listBibl>
         <bibl xml:id="ScLe">
            <title>The Scarlet Letter</title>
            <author>Nathaniel Hawthorne</author>
            <date>1850</date>
            <idno type="ISBN">978-1512090567</idno>
         </bibl>
         <bibl xml:id="NT">
            <title>Neues Testament</title>
            <idno type="VIAF">223078470</idno>
         </bibl>
      </listBibl>
      <list>
         <item xml:id="def_schism">
            <term>Schism</term>
            <gloss>When there is a schism, a group or organization divides into two groups as a
               result of differences in thinking and beliefs.</gloss>
            <cit type="example">
               <quote>...the great schism which divided the Christian world in the 11th
                  century.</quote>
            </cit>
         </item>
         <item xml:id="def_tool">
            <term>Tool</term>
            <gloss>Tool is an American rock band from Los Angeles. Formed in 1990, the group's
               line-up includes vocalist Maynard James Keenan, guitarist Adam Jones and drummer
               Danny Carey. Justin Chancellor has been the band's bassist since 1995, replacing
               their original bassist Paul D'Amour. Tool has won four Grammy Awards, performed
               worldwide tours, and produced albums topping the charts in several countries.</gloss>
            <idno type="VIAF">133634298</idno>
         </item>
         <item xml:id="def_lat">
            <term>Lateralus</term>
            <gloss>Lateralus (/ˌlætəˈræləs/)[2] is the third studio album by American rock band
               Tool. It was released on May 15, 2001, through Volcano Entertainment. The album was
               recorded at Cello Studios in Hollywood and The Hook, Big Empty Space, and The Lodge,
               in North Hollywood, between October 2000 and January 2001.</gloss>
         </item>
         <item xml:id="def_apc">
            <term>A Perfect Circle</term>
            <gloss>A Perfect Circle is an American rock band formed in Los Angeles, California in
               1999 by guitarist Billy Howerdel and Tool vocalist Maynard James Keenan.</gloss>
            <idno type="VIAF">138599085</idno>
         </item>
         <item xml:id="def_HeQa">
            <term>Hermetic Qabalah</term>
            <gloss>Hermetic Qabalah (from Hebrew קַבָּלָה (qabalah) 'reception, accounting') is a
               Western esoteric tradition involving mysticism and the occult.</gloss>
         </item>
         <item xml:id="def_Seph">
            <term>Sephiroth</term>
            <gloss>Sephiroth is the hebrew is the Hebrew term of the ten divine emanations in the
               Kabbalistic Tree of Life.</gloss>
         </item>
         <item xml:id="def_VoEn">
            <term>Volcano Entertainment</term>
            <gloss>Volcano Entertainment (sometimes referred to as Volcano Records) was an American
               all-round music record label founded in 1996.</gloss>
            <idno type="VIAF">150299175</idno>
         </item>
         <item xml:id="def_FiSe">
            <term>Fibonacci sequence</term>
            <gloss>In mathematics, the Fibonacci numbers, form a sequence, the Fibonacci sequence,
               in which each number is the sum of the two preceding ones. Starting from 0 and 1, the
               next few values in the sequence are: 0, 1, 1, 2, 3, 5, 8, 13, 21, 34, 55, 89, 144,
               ...</gloss>
         </item>
      </list>
   </standOff>
   <text>
      <front>
         <p>The following is a text, containing the lyrics and it´s interpretation from <ref
               target="#def_tool">Tool</ref>´s Album "<ref target="#def_lat">Lateralus</ref>". <ref
               target="#def_lat">Lateralus</ref> is their third studio album. It was released on
               <date when="2001-05-15">May 15, 2001</date>, through <ref target="#def_VoEn">Volcano
               Entertainment</ref>. The album was recorded at Cello Studios in
               <placeName>Hollywood</placeName> and The Hook, Big Empty Space, and The Lodge, in
               <placeName>North Hollywood</placeName>, between <date>October 2000</date> and
               <date>January 2001</date>. <persName>David Bottrill</persName>, who had produced the
            band's two previous releases <name>Ænima</name> and <name>Salival</name>, produced the
            album along with the band, and became the last <ref target="#def_tool">Tool</ref> album
            produced by <persName>Bottrill</persName> to date. The tracklist looks as follows: <list
               type="tracklist">
               <item xml:id="lat_1">1."The Grudge"</item>
               <item xml:id="lat_2">2. "Eon Blue Apocalypse" (instrumental)</item>
               <item xml:id="lat_3">3. "The Patient"</item>
               <item xml:id="lat_4">4. "Mantra" (instrumental)</item>
               <item xml:id="lat_5">5. "Schism"</item>
               <item xml:id="lat_6">6. "Parabol"</item>
               <item xml:id="lat_7">7. "Parabola"</item>
               <item xml:id="lat_8">8. "Ticks &amp; Leeches"</item>
               <item xml:id="lat_9">9. "Lateralus"</item>
               <item xml:id="lat_10">10. "Disposition"</item>
               <item xml:id="lat_11">11. "Reflection"</item>
               <item xml:id="lat_12">12. "Triad" (instrumental)</item>
               <item xml:id="lat_13">13. "Faaip de Oiad"</item>
            </list></p>
      </front>
      <body>
         <head>Encoding of songtexts from Tools Album "Lateralus" and their interpretation</head>
         <div type="song" n="1" corresp="#lat_1">
            <head>1. The Grudge</head>
            <note corresp="#lat_1">“The Grudge” is a song about maturity and development, using
               alchemical, astrological, and mythological symbolism.</note>
            <lg type="chorus" n="1.1." xml:id="grudge_chor1">
               <l xml:id="line_1.1.1.">Wear your grudge like a crown of negativity.</l>
               <l>Calculate what we will or will not tolerate.</l>
               <l>Desperate to control all and everything.</l>
               <l xml:id="line_1.1.4.">Unable to forgive your scarlet lettermen.</l>
               <note corresp="#line_1.1.1.">A crown is a symbol of power, a source of authority, but
                  also a burden of responsibility. Here, the grudge, being a feeling of resentment
                  against perceived wrongdoers, acts as a “negative” crown which one chooses to
                  wear. It is a symbol of power because it lets you feel hatred toward the
                  transgressors, and of authority because it lets you stand separate from them. In
                  the <ref target="#def_HeQa">Hermetic Qabalah</ref>, which alchemists and
                  hermeticists connect with astrology and alchemy, the highest <ref
                     target="#def_Seph">Sephiroth</ref> on the Tree of Life diagram is called
                  Kether, which in Hebrew means “Crown.” Kether is directly connected to Binah
                  (“Understanding”), which is attributed to Saturn.</note>
               <note corresp="#line_1.1.4.">This line refers to the classic novel <name ref="#ScLe"
                     >The Scarlet Letter</name> by <name ref="#NaHa">Nathaniel Hawthorne</name>,
                  largely seen as symbolic or even allegorical. The main character Hester Prynne is
                  an adulteress who is forced to wear a scarlet letter ‘A’ on her breast as
                  punishment for committing adultery with Arthur Dimmesdale, Puritan minister and
                  the father of her child, Pearl. Lettermens deliver messages. So the one who can´t
                  forgive the scarlet lettermen is one who can´t forgive those who accuse him of
                  something shameful</note>
            </lg>
            <lg type="verse" n="1.2." xml:id="grudge_vers1">
               <l xml:id="line_1.2.1.">Clutch it like a cornerstone.</l>
               <l xml:id="line_1.2.2.">Otherwise it all comes down.</l>
               <l xml:id="line_1.2.3.">Justify denials and</l>
               <l xml:id="line_1.2.4.">grip it to the lonesome end.</l>
               <l>Clutch it like a cornerstone.</l>
               <l>Otherwise it all comes down.</l>
               <l>Terrified of being wrong.</l>
               <l>Ultimatum prison cell.</l>
               <note corresp="#line_1.2.1., #line_1.2.2.">The cornerstone is the first stone set in
                  the construction of a masonry foundation and is important since all other stones
                  will be set in reference to this stone, thus determining the position of the
                  entire structure. The cornerstone metaphor serves a dual purpose; it depicts the
                  titular grudge as a defining personal characteristic, holding everything in place,
                  but it also suggests a burden to keep it aloft. Hence the later mention of an
                  "ultimatum prison cell"</note>
               <note corresp="#line_1.2.3., #line_1.2.4.">For the protagonist it is important to
                  justify refusals and disapproval in order to evade their meaning. And so in fear
                  of being offended he/she is afraid of bonding to his/her fellows.</note>
            </lg>
            <lg type="refrain" n="1.3." xml:id="grudge_ref1">
               <l>Saturn ascends,</l>
               <l xml:id="line_1.3.2.">choose one or ten.</l>
               <l>Hang on or be</l>
               <l>humbled again.</l>
               <note corresp="#grudge_ref1">The refrain references to a astrological as well as to a
                  mythological fact. In mythological sence speaking the Roman god Saturn is
                  ascending by castrating and finally dispatching his father Caelus, the god of the
                  sky and ruler of the universe (Uranus in Greek myth). The phrase “comes around
                  again” references to the circumstance when Saturn is overthrown by his son
                  Jupiter. It is the editors belief, that the mythological killing of ones father is
                  the process of individuation. The figure of the father is the representation of
                  the mind and culture(in contrast to the mother which is a symbol for the material
                  world) and it is the duty of one to break free from his automated mind and stop
                  reacting to the outside world in preconseived notions. Astrologically speaking
                  every 29 years the planet Saturn arrives at the same place as when he was at ones
                  birth. It is said, that the time around "Saturns return" - so around age 29, 58
                  and 87 - is impactful for the individual for one starts to rethink embarked paths
                  and become more mature. If one is not able to let go of the emotional tidal waves
                  of pain, anger and frustration and order ones life more truthfully and less
                  compulsive around that time, it will be hard for one to change that until the next
                  29 years have passed. <note corresp="#line_1.3.2.">Choose one or ten is a
                     reference to the Sephiroth of the Kabbalistic Tree of Life. One is Kether, the
                     Crown, the first emanation from God, while ten is Malkuth, or Kingdom, the last
                     Sephira and considered the lowest emanation.</note></note>
            </lg>
            <lg type="verse" n="1.4" xml:id="grudge_vers2">
               <l>Clutch it like a cornerstone.</l>
               <l>Otherwise it all comes down.</l>
               <l>Justify denials and</l>
               <l>grip it to the lonesome end.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="refrain" n="1.5." xml:id="grudge_ref2">
               <l>Saturn ascends,</l>
               <l>comes round again.</l>
               <l>Saturn ascends</l>
               <l>the one, the ten.</l>
               <l>Ignorant to the damage done.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="chorus" n="1.6." sameAs="#grudge_chor1">
               <l>Wear your grudge like a crown of negativity.</l>
               <l>Calculate what you will or will not tolerate.</l>
               <l>Desperate to control all and everything.</l>
               <l>Unable to forgive your scarlet lettermen.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="verse" n="1.7." xml:id="grudge_vers3">
               <l>Wear the grudge like a crown.</l>
               <l>Desperate to control.</l>
               <l>Unable to forgive.</l>
               <l>And we're sinking deeper.</l>
               <l>Defining, confining, sinking deeper.</l>
               <l>Controlling, defining,</l>
               <l>and we're sinking deeper.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="chorus" n="1.8." xml:id="grudge_chor2">
               <l>Saturn comes back around to show you everything</l>
               <l>Let's you choose what you will not see and then</l>
               <l>Drags you down like a stone or lifts you up again</l>
               <l xml:id="line_1.8.4.">Spits you out like a child, light and innocent.</l>
               <note corresp="#grudge_chor2">The metaphor is about Saturn (a symbol of time and
                  maturity) giving perspective to either lift you up as you choose to forgive
                  yourself and those who raised you for the way you were raised in your early life,
                  or letting that reality drag you down to a lower state of blame, resentment, and
                  anger.</note>
               <note corresp="#line_1.8.4.">In a Roman myth, upon learning that one of his sons
                  would excel him, Saturn begins to eat his children. Opis, a fertility goddess and
                  Jupiter’s mother, swaddles a stone in Jupiter’s place and Saturn ends up eating it
                  instead.</note>
            </lg>
            <lg type="bridge" n="1.9." xml:id="grudge_bridge">
               <l>Saturn comes back around.</l>
               <l>Lifts you up like a child or</l>
               <l>Drags you down like a stone to</l>
               <l>Consume you till you</l>
               <l>choose to let this go.</l>
               <l>Choose to let this go.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="verse" n="1.10." xml:id="grudge_vers4">
               <l>Give away the stone.</l>
               <l>Let the oceans take and transmutate</l>
               <l>this cold and fated anchor.</l>
               <l>Give away the stone.</l>
               <l xml:id="line_1.10.5.">Let the waters kiss and transmutate</l>
               <l xml:id="line_1.10.6.">these leaden grudges into gold.</l>
               <note corresp="#line_1.10.5., #line_1.10.6.">Alchemy is, superficially, the attempt
                  to transmute lead into gold – lead being a dull, heavy, and even harmful metal,
                  and gold superconductive, beautiful and valuable. Underneath the symbol, however,
                  the Swiss psychologist <name ref="#CaJu">Carl Jung</name> saw within a symbolic
                  process that he used to create his system of psychological development called
                  individuation. It is the process by which an individual conscious self develops
                  out of undifferentiated consciousness. In alchemy, Saturn’s metal is lead, while
                  gold is attributed to the Sun.</note>
            </lg>
            <lg type="outro" n="1.11." xml:id="grudge_outro">
               <l>Let go.</l>
               <note corresp="#grudge_outro">The final line of the song adds clarity to the rest of
                  the lyrics: it tells the grudge holder to forgive and let go. This sentiment is
                  repeated again in <name ref="#lat_3">schism</name>.</note>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="song" n="3" corresp="#lat_3">
            <head>3. The Patient</head>
            <note corresp="#lat_3">This song is written from the perspective of the singer’s mother.
               She has been paralyzed since <date>1976</date>. In this song we see his mother
               battling not only with herself, her illness and the way it affects the ones she loves
               (referred to in the beginning as <ref target="#line_3.1.2.">"the fearful"</ref>) but
               also her faith. <ref target="#line_3.1.3.">In the song there are multiple instances
                  where she questions what’s happening to her and God’s masterplan and how it can be
                  that this is the path that was chosen for her.</ref>
            </note>
            <lg type="verse" n="3.1." xml:id="thepat_vers1">
               <l>A groan of tedium escapes me,</l>
               <l xml:id="line_3.1.2.">startling the fearful.</l>
               <l xml:id="line_3.1.3.">Is this a test? It has to be.</l>
               <l>Otherwise I can't go on.</l>
               <l>Draining patience. drain vitality.</l>
               <l>this paranoid, paralyzed vampire act's a little old.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="verse" n="3.2." xml:id="thepat_vers2">
               <l>But I'm still right here,</l>
               <l>giving blood and keeping faith.</l>
               <l>And I'm still right here.</l>
               <l>But I'm still right here,</l>
               <l>giving blood and keeping faith.</l>
               <l>And I'm still right here.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="pre-chorus" n="3.3." xml:id="thepat_prechor">
               <l>I'm gonna wait it out</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="chorus" n="3.4." xml:id="thepat_chor1">
               <l>If there were no rewards to reap,</l>
               <l>no loving embrace to see me through</l>
               <l>this tedious path I've chosen here,</l>
               <l>I certainly would've walked away by now.</l>
               <l>I'm gonna wait it out</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="chorus" n="3.5." xml:id="thepat_chor2">
               <l>If there were no desire to heal</l>
               <l>The damaged and broken met along</l>
               <l>this tedious path I've chosen here,</l>
               <l>I certainly would've walked away by now.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="bridge" n="3.6." xml:id="thepat_bridge">
               <l>I still may.</l>
               <l>And I still may.</l>
               <l>Be patient.</l>
               <l>I must keep reminding myself of this...</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="chorus" n="3.7." xml:id="thepat_chor3">
               <l>If there were no rewards to reap,</l>
               <l>no loving embrace to see me through</l>
               <l>this tedious path I've chosen here,</l>
               <l>I certainly would've walked away by now.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="outro" n="3.8." xml:id="thepat_outro">
               <l>And I still may.</l>
               <l>And I still may.</l>
               <l>And I still may.</l>
               <l>I'm gonna wait it out.</l>
               <l>I'm gonna wait it out.</l>
               <l>Gonna wait it out.</l>
               <l>Gonna wait it out.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="song" n="5" corresp="#lat_5">
            <head>5. Schism</head>
            <note corresp="#lat_5">In this song, lead singer <ref target="#MaJaKe">Maynard James
                  Keenan</ref> describes the effect a <ref target="#def_schism">“schism”</ref> can
               have on a relationship when the parties disagree and communications break down. This
               song and all of <ref target="#def_lat">Lateralus</ref> came after some rough legal
               issues with record labels and the success of Maynard’s other band, <ref
                  target="#def_apc">A Perfect Circle</ref>, which had just started to require a lot
               more of his time. This song is Tool’s “Come Together” in that it is there way of
               letting fans and even themselves know that even if there have been hardships they can
               still fit together and create greatness. He uses a jigsaw puzzle as a metaphor for
               the relationship.On the album the song is introduced by the interlude “<ref
                  target="#lat_4">Mantra</ref>.” The interlude is included in the <ref
                  target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UhjG47gtMCo">music video</ref> .</note>
            <lg type="verse" n="5.1." xml:id="schism_vers1">
               <l>I know the pieces fit</l>
               <l>cuz I watched them fall away</l>
               <l>mildewed and smoldering,</l>
               <l>fundamental differing,</l>
               <l>pure intention juxtaposed</l>
               <l>will set two lovers souls in motion</l>
               <l>disintegrating as it goes</l>
               <l>testing our communication</l>
               <note corresp="#schism_vers1">The relationship once with integrity (like a jigsaw
                  puzzle put together) is now falling apart. But it can be reassembled again, since
                  the pieces were together at some point. If the two parties are able to integrate
                  their different beliefs, they could save the relationship</note>
            </lg>
            <lg type="bridge" n="5.2." xml:id="schism_bridge1">
               <l>the light that fueled our fire then</l>
               <l>has burned a hole between us so</l>
               <l>we cannot <sic>see</sic> to reach an end</l>
               <l>crippling our communication.</l>
               <note corresp="#schism_bridge1">The same passion that brought the two together now
                  fans the flames of their bitterness. Also the fighting never stops. One fight
                  leads to another, and there is no stepping back to let things calm down. Instead
                  of communication there is only fighting.</note>
            </lg>
            <lg type="verse" n="5.3." xml:id="schism_vers2">
               <l>I know the pieces fit</l>
               <l>cuz I watched them tumble down</l>
               <l xml:id="line_5.3.3.">no fault, none to blame</l>
               <l xml:id="line_5.3.4.">it doesn't mean I don't desire</l>
               <l xml:id="line_5.3.5.">to point the finger, blame the other,</l>
               <l xml:id="line_5.3.6.">watch the temple topple over.</l>
               <l>To bring the pieces back together,</l>
               <l>rediscover communication.</l>
               <note corresp="#line_5.3.3., #line_5.3.4., #line_5.3.5.">There is no fault because
                  both are fighting for something they believe in. Despite this fact,or maybe
                  because of the purity of his intentions, he still feels the desire to lay all of
                  the blame at the others feet. Ignoring that they are coming from an equal
                  place.</note>
               <note corresp="#line_5.3.6."> This line refers to the cleansing of the Temple
                  narrative, which tells of <ref target="#JeChNa">Jesus</ref> expelling the
                  merchants and the money changers from the Temple. It is recounted in all four
                  canonical gospels of the <ref target="#NT">New Testament</ref>. The temple is a
                  synonym for the relationship. Both can serve for holy purposes. But if the
                  intentions become distorted, the profane will rush in.</note>
            </lg>
            <lg type="bridge" n="5.4." xml:id="schism_bridge2">
               <l>The poetry that comes from the squaring off between,</l>
               <l>And the circling is worth it.</l>
               <l>Finding beauty in the dissonance.</l>
               <note corresp="#schism_bridge2">The author compares their struggles to a boxing match
                  (squaring off, circling), and is finding beauty in the passion of their fighting
                  (beauty in dissonance).</note>
            </lg>
            <lg type="verse" n="5.5." xml:id="schism_vers3">
               <l>There was a time that the pieces fit,</l>
               <l>but I watched them fall away.</l>
               <l>Mildewed and smoldering,</l>
               <l xml:id="line_5.5.4.">strangled by our coveting</l>
               <l xml:id="line_5.5.5.">I've done the <sic>the</sic> math enough to know</l>
               <l xml:id="line_5.5.6.">the dangers of a second guessing</l>
               <l>Doomed to crumble unless we grow,</l>
               <l>and strengthen our communication</l>
            </lg>
            <note corresp="#line_5.5.4., #line_5.5.5., #line_5.5.6.">To covet means to desire. So
               the relationship gets "strangled" by desire - either of another person, or of being
               right. The protagonist knows that this is very dangerous to the relationship. By
               wanting someone else, they are second guessing their decision to be in an exclusive
               relationship.</note>
            <lg type="bridge" n="5.6." xml:id="schism_bridge3">
               <l xml:id="line_5.6.1.">cold silence has a tendency to</l>
               <l xml:id="line_5.6.2.">atrophy any sense of compassion</l>
               <l xml:id="line_5.6.3.">between supposed lovers</l>
               <l xml:id="line_5.6.4.">between supposed brothers.</l>
            </lg>
            <note corresp="#line_5.6.1., #line_5.6.2.">The theme of passive aggressive behavior runs
               through this song like a river. Being passive-aggressive is destructive behavior and
               these two lines attempt to clarify that. The sentiment is quite universal, but the
               words that the songwriters chose here are what communicates the weight of the
               meaning. Cold silence is more than just refusing to talk to each other; it is a
               deeply rooted commitment to avoid communication. It starts as a seed, a slight or
               offense, and grows as it’s fed with negativity and a steadfast refusal to yield or
               tolerate. Also, consider the use of the word “atrophy”. For a living organism, to
               have a part atrophy is more than just to get sore from not moving during an extended
               binge of a show or video game. The atrophy of something takes time and is defined as
               “arrested development or loss of a part or organ incidental to the normal development
               or life of an animal or plant”. Atrophy is the literal wasting away of a part of you
               because it is not being used. In this setting, the wasting away of one’s sense of
               compassion because you just can’t find a way to overcome your disagreement.</note>
            <note corresp="#line_5.6.3., #line_5.6.4.">The word supposed is important here. By title
               they are lovers but with all of the fighting and the breakdown in communication it no
               longer feels so. By using “supposed” he illustrates how the breakdown of the
               relationship has strained their bond, and that the way they treat each other isn’t
               how two lovers treat their significant other.</note>
            <lg type="outro" n="5.7." xml:id="schism_outro">
               <l>And I know the pieces fit.</l>
            </lg>
            <note corresp="#schism_outro">Reading the text one might have the impression that the
               protagonist matured enough to let go of his resentment - as it is referenced in <ref
                  target="#lat_1">the first song of the album</ref>. But listening to the Outro of
               the song the words "I know the pieces fit" sound aggressive as if the protagonist
               wants to force the relationship into harmony. However as we learned throughout the
               song a schism must be overcome in order for the relationship to function.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="song" n="6" corresp="#lat_6">
            <head>6. Parabol</head>
            <note corresp="#lat_6">This song is a prelude to the song “<ref target="#lat_7"
                  >Parabola</ref>”. It is lyrically very similar to “<ref target="#lat_7"
                  >Parabola</ref>” and serves as a more calm opener to the heavier sound of “<ref
                  target="#lat_7">Parabola</ref>”. The song describes human existence and our own
               spirit and bodies in an eternal sense. It illustrates the idea that life is just a
               place to prepare our spirits for some kind of eternal cycle or state of being,
               whatever that may be.</note>
            <lg type="verse" n="6.1." xml:id="par_vers1">
               <l>So familiar and overwhelmingly warm</l>
               <l>This one, this form I hold now.</l>
               <l>Embracing you, this reality here,</l>
               <l>This one, this form I hold now, so</l>
               <l>Wide eyed and hopeful.</l>
               <l>Wide eyed and hopefully wild.</l>
               <l>We barely remember what came before this precious moment,</l>
               <l>Choosing to be here right now.</l>
               <l>Hold on, stay inside...</l>
               <l>This body holding me,</l>
               <l>reminding me that I am not alone in</l>
               <l>This body makes me feel eternal.</l>
               <l>All this pain is an illusion.</l>
            </lg>
            <note>The author takes a step back and percieves himself as different from his body -
               him being just pure awareness. That he is aware of his "familiar" body may imply that
               the awareness which he identifies as was present in other bodies before. He holds
               this form just temporarily, looking forward to being released again after the death
               of the body - remembering again what happened before we were born. He as awareness is
               choosing to be in the present moment - not concealed by the automated minds chatter
               consisting of thoughts and emotions. The knowing of him being the awareness - not the
               body or the mind - let´s him see beyond the suffering of the individual.</note>
         </div>
         <div type="song" n="7" corresp="#lat_7">
            <head>7. Parabola</head>
            <note corresp="#lat_7">A “parabola” is a U-shaped curve in a quadratic function in which
               any point has the same distance from a fixed straight line. “Parabola” is a play on
               the title of the introduction section, titled “Parabol,” which is a play on the word
               “parable,” or a story with an intended moral lesson. Parables form the foundation for
               all modern major religions. The song “Parabola” builds on the interlude musically as
               well as thematically as it tells about the celebration of life, the “holy experience”
               of birth, and the unlikely opportunity that we all share to be temporarily conscious
               of each other and the world around us. <ref target="#line_7.3.1.">This song focuses
                  on the realization through our bodily experience that others share the same
                  limitations and desires as we do</ref>, and we will all eventually fade back into
               nothingness, as we were before our births. This realization “of our own mortality”
               urges us to treasure the life we have, use it to the best of our ability, and ignore
               base, unnecessary, unfulfuillable desires that detract from the richness of our
               experience of life.</note>
            <lg type="verse" n="7.1." xml:id="para_vers1">
               <l>We barely remember</l>
               <l>who or what came before this precious moment,</l>
               <l>We are <sic>Choosing</sic> to be here right now.</l>
               <l>Hold on, stay inside...</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="pre-chorus" n="7.2." xml:id="para_prechor1">
               <l>This holy reality,</l>
               <l>this holy experience.</l>
               <l>Choosing to be here in...</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="chorus" n="7.3." xml:id="para_chor1">
               <l xml:id="line_7.3.1.">This body. This body holding me.</l>
               <l>Be my reminder here that I am not alone in</l>
               <l>This body, this body holding me,</l>
               <l>feeling eternal all this pain is an illusion.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="post-chorus" n="7.4." xml:id="para_postchor">
               <l>Alive</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="pre-chorus" n="7.5." xml:id="para_prechor2">
               <l>This holy reality,</l>
               <l>in this holy experience.</l>
               <l>Choosing to be here in...</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="chorus" n="7.6." xml:id="para_chor2">
               <l>This body. This body holding me.</l>
               <l>Be my reminder here that I am not alone in</l>
               <l>This body, this body holding me,</l>
               <l>feeling eternal all this pain is an illusion...</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="bridge" n="7.7." xml:id="para_bridge">
               <l>Of what it means to be alive</l>
               <l>Swirling round with this familiar parable.</l>
               <l>Spinning, weaving round each new experience.</l>
               <l>Recognize this as a holy gift and</l>
               <l>celebrate this chance to be alive and breathing</l>
               <l>chance to be alive and breathing.</l>
               <note corresp="#para_bridge">The familiar parable may be the life process for life
                  and death balance each other out. Pure consciousness, which acts as the
                  protagonist in this song so to speak, experiences this parable again and again and
                  integrates the experiences of all human beings. Humans in turn should become aware
                  of their true nature (awareness) and become greatful for their role.</note>
            </lg>
            <lg type="outro" n="7.8." xml:id="para_outro">
               <l>This body holding me reminds me of my own mortality.</l>
               <l>Embrace this moment. Remember.</l>
               <l>we are eternal. all this pain is an illusion.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="song" n="8" corresp="#lat_8">
            <head>8. Ticks &amp; Leeches</head>
            <note corresp="#lat_8">Off of “<ref target="#def_lat">Lateralus</ref>”, this
               thinly-veiled allegory denounces record executives and the music industry for taking
               advantage of artists' effort and sacrifices and in so picking up the theme from "<ref
                  target="#lat_5">Schism</ref>" in which two parties have two different opinions.
               All against the background of some rough legal issues with their former record label
                  "<ref target="#def_VoEn">Volcano Entertainment</ref>" just before recording the
               album. Because of financial troubles the band attempted to leave the label which
               resuled in a lenghty lawsuit. Those individuals are compared to parasites for
               demanding more while giving nothing.</note>
            <lg type="verse" n="8.1." xml:id="TaL_vers1">
               <l>Suck and suck.</l>
               <l>Suckin up all you can</l>
               <l>suckin up all you can suck.</l>
               <l>Workin up under my patience like a little tick.</l>
               <l>Fat little parasite.</l>
               <l>Suck me dry.</l>
               <l>My blood is bruised and borrowed.</l>
               <l>You thieving bastards.</l>
               <l>You have turned my blood cold and bitter,</l>
               <l>beat my compassion black and blue.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="chorus" n="8.2." xml:id="TaL_chorus1">
               <l>Hope this is what you wanted.</l>
               <l>Hope this is what you had in mind.</l>
               <l>Cuz this is what you're getting.</l>
               <l>I hope you're choking.</l>
               <l>I hope you choke on this.</l>
               <l>I hope you're choking.</l>
               <l>I hope you choke on this.</l>
               <note corresp="#TaL_chorus1">Maybe the record label - already in financial troubles -
                  lost the case and artists who signed a contract left them in so comming to a
                  financial ruin.</note>
            </lg>
            <lg type="verse" n="8.3." xml:id="TaL_verse2">
               <l>Taken all I can taken all I can, we can take.</l>
               <l>Taken all you can taken you can, we can take.</l>
               <l>Got nothing left to give to you.</l>
               <l>Blood suckin parasitic little blood suckin parasitic</l>
               <l>little blood suckin parasitic little tick</l>
               <l>Take what you want and then go.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="bridge" n="8.4." xml:id="TaL_bridge">
               <l>Suck me dry.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="chorus" n="8.5." xml:id="TaL_chor2">
               <l>Is this what you wanted?</l>
               <l>Is this what you had in mind?</l>
               <l>Is this what you wanted?</l>
               <l>Cuz this this is what you're getting.</l>
               <l>I hope, I hope, I hope you choke.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="song" n="9" corresp="#lat_9">
            <head>9. Lateralus</head>
            <note corresp="#lat_9">“Lateralus” is one of the most overtly intricate songs by Tool.
               The predominant lyrical theme is that over-analysis leads to loss of control, linear
               structures don’t exist in nature and that we “should embrace the random”. Ironically,
               the song, as well as the entire album’s, structure was carefully planned; this
               specific song is based on the <ref target="#def_FiSe">Fibonacci sequence</ref>: The
               introduction section of the song is 01:12 long (0, 1, 1, 2 are the first four numbers
               in the sequence). The first verse starts at 97 seconds, which is approximately 1.618
               minutes – (The Golden Ratio). Each verse is 55 seconds long (11th # in sequence). The
               syllables in the verses coincide with the sequence, as the first part of the first
               verse goes 1, 1, 2, 3, 5, 8, 5, 3. The 2nd line “to swing on the spiral” finishes at
               6:18 which numerically matches 1.618 – (The Golden Ratio). The time signature of the
               main riff is 9/8 8/8 7/8, 987 is the 17th term in the sequence. So as a sort of
               double-standard, this song wants you to embrace the random, but “embracing” could be
               interpreted as such for studying its anomalies, which in turn could be found as over
               analysis.</note>
            <lg type="verse" n="9.1." xml:id="lat_vers1">
               <l met="+/">Black</l>
               <l met="+/">then</l>
               <l met="+|+/">white are</l>
               <l met="+|+|+/">all i see</l>
               <l met="+|+|+|-|-/">in my infancy.</l>
               <l met="+|+|+|-|+|+|+|+/">red and yellow then came to be,</l>
               <l met="+|-|+|+|+/">reaching out to me.</l>
               <l met="+|+|+/">lets me see.</l>
               <interp>This verse is a reference to the first two steps in the alchemical Magnum
                  Opus or ‘great work’ to attain the Philosopher’s Stone. The Magnum Opus has become
                  a metaphor for many things; from practical chemical processes to spirituality and
                  philosophy. In the alchemical tradition, Nigredo (black) is the first stage and
                  Albedo (white) is the second, followed by Citrinitas (yellow) and Rubedo (red).
                  The word “infancy” works on both literal and figurative levels. Actual human
                  infants do perceive the world in black and white as their senses begin to develop,
                  before seeing red as their first primary color. Additionally, the term “infancy”
                  suggests a metaphor for the progression of human consciousness. Our first
                  impressions of reality are simplistic, initially tending towards duality (good and
                  evil, friend and foe etc.), whereas intellectual maturity relies upon
                  incorporating other elements into our perspective. The syllables in the verses and
                  the comming pre-choruses conform with the Fibonacci sequence.</interp>
            </lg>
            <lg type="pre-chorus" n="9.2." xml:id="lat_prechor">
               <l met="+|-|+|+|-|+|+|-|+|+|-|+|+/" xml:id="line_9.2.1.">as below, so above and
                  beyond, I imagine</l>
               <l met="+|-|+|+|+|+|+|-/">drawn beyond the lines of reason.</l>
               <l met="+|+|+|-|-/">Push the envelope.</l>
               <l met="+|+|+/">Watch it bend.</l>
               <note corresp="#line_9.2.1.">This is a reference to the Hermetism’s Law of
                  Correspondence, it states that this principle manifests in the three Great Planes
                  of Existence: the mental plane, physical plane and spiritual plane. This law talks
                  about the harmony between the Great Planes of Existence, the division of them in
                  different categories is artificial and arbitrary, in fact, there’s no such
                  separation.</note>
            </lg>
            <lg type="chorus" n="9.3." xml:id="lat_chor1">
               <l>Over thinking, over analyzing separates the body from the mind.</l>
               <l>Withering my intuition, missing opportunities and I must</l>
            </lg>
            <note corresp="#lat_chor1">Over thinking and over analyzing can lead you to be
               hopelessly cautious when considering the motions and actions you execute. This seems
               to be ironical, when one looks at the song´s structure.</note>
            <lg type="post-chorus" n="9.4." xml:id="lat_postchor1">
               <l>Feed my will to feel my moment</l>
               <l>drawing way outside the lines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="verse" n="9.5." sameAs="#lat_vers1">
               <l met="+/">Black</l>
               <l met="+/">then</l>
               <l met="+|+/">white are</l>
               <l met="+|+|+/">all i see</l>
               <l met="+|+|+|-|-/">in my infancy.</l>
               <l met="+|+|+|-|+|+|+|+/">red and yellow then came to be,</l>
               <l met="+|-|+|+|+/">reaching out to me.</l>
               <l met="+|+|+/">lets me see.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="verse" n="9.6." xml:id="lat_vers2">
               <l met="+|+/">there is</l>
               <l met="+/">so</l>
               <l met="+/">much</l>
               <l met="+|+/">more and</l>
               <l met="+|-|+/">beckons me</l>
               <l met="+|+|+|+|+/">to look thru to these</l>
               <l met="+|-|-|+|-|+|-|-/">infinite possibilities.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="pre-chorus" n="9.7." sameAs="#lat_prechor">
               <l met="+|-|+|+|-|+|+|-|+|+|-|+|+/">as below, so above and beyond, I imagine</l>
               <l met="+|-|+|+|+|+|+|-/">drawn beyond the lines of reason.</l>
               <l met="+|+|+|-|-/">Push the envelope.</l>
               <l met="+|+|+/">Watch it bend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="chorus" n="9.8." xml:id="lat_chor2">
               <l>Over thinking, over analyzing separates the body from the mind.</l>
               <l>Withering my intuition leaving opportunities behind.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="post-chorus" n="9.9." xml:id="lat_postchor2">
               <l>Feed my will to feel my moment</l>
               <l>urging me to cross the line.</l>
               <l>Reaching out to embrace the random.</l>
               <l>Reaching out to embrace whatever may come.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="bridge" n="9.10." xml:id="lat_bridge">
               <l>I embrace my desire to</l>
               <l>I embrace my desire to</l>
               <l>feel the rhythm,</l>
               <l>to feel connected</l>
               <l>enough to step aside and</l>
               <l>weep like a widow</l>
               <l>to feel inspired</l>
               <l>to fathom the power,</l>
               <l>to witness the beauty,</l>
               <l>to bathe in the fountain,</l>
               <l xml:id="line_9.10.11.">to swing on the spiral</l>
               <l>to swing on the spiral</l>
               <l>to swing on the spiral</l>
               <l>of our divinity and</l>
               <l>still be a human.</l>
               <note corresp="#lat_bridge">To stop the thinking process, the protagonist tries to
                  "step aside" from what he believes he is. From this viewpoint he can have empathy
                  with himself and so letting pent up emotions by weeping.</note>
               <note corresp="#line_9.10.11.">The Fibonacci sequence in geometry defines what’s
                  known as the “golden spiral,” an ever-expanding spiral figure seen frequently in
                  nature (such as the patterns of seeds in sunflowers or the shell of a nautilus).
                  These later references to “the spiral” serve as confirmation of the intentional
                  Fibonacci coding throughout in the song. This also adds on to the theme of
                  “embracing the random,” as seen throughout the song, by not overthinking and just
                  following the spiral.</note>
            </lg>
            <lg type="outro" n="9.11." xml:id="lat_outro">
               <l>With my feet upon the ground</l>
               <l>I move myeslf between the sounds</l>
               <l>and open wide to suck it in.</l>
               <l>I feel it move across my skin.</l>
               <l>I'm reaching up and reaching out.</l>
               <l>I'm reaching for the random or</l>
               <l>what ever will bewilder me.</l>
               <l>what ever will bewilder me.</l>
               <l>And following our will and wind</l>
               <l>we may just go where no one's been.</l>
               <l>We'll ride the spiral to the end</l>
               <l>and may just go where no one's been.</l>
               <l>Spiral out. Keep going.</l>
               <l>Spiral out. Keep going.</l>
               <l>Spiral out. Keep going.</l>
               <l>Spiral out. Keep going.</l>
               <l>Spiral out. Keep going.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
         <div type="song" n="10" corresp="#lat_10">
            <head>10. Disposition</head>
            <lg type="verse" n="10.1." xml:id="disp_vers">
               <l>mention this to me. mention something, anything..</l>
               <l>and watch the weather change.</l>
            </lg>

         </div>
         <note corresp="#lat_10">This song is about both kinds of realities humans can experience -
            the psychological and existential reality. Without a certain amount of awareness to our
            thought-process, we are prone (hence the name of the song "Disposition") to live in a
            parallel reality, consisting just of thoughts and emotions - the psychological reality.
            Everything in existence is working out fine - the planets follow their orbit, the sun
            comes up regulary on time (if it wouldn´t, almost every life on this planet would be
            gone in 18 hours), our hearts beat just the way they need to and our digestive system
            makes sure that we are provided with nutrients. And still if we live in a psychological
            reality where we are mostly occupied with our thoughts and emotions, identified with our
            body and mind, we would dismiss these things as obvious and ignoring our true nature -
            the life process inherit in all living things. The desperate need of the intellect for
            thought feeds this psychological reality if it happens compulsive ("mention this to me.
            mention something, anything.."). Thoughts create emotion and the other way around.
            Overemphasising the way we feel at the moment we tend to stay in this loop. The antitode
            to these compulsions of the mind is to pay attention to what lies beyond the mind and
            body and observe the everchanging existence ("and watch the weather change").</note>
         <div type="song" n="11" corresp="#lat_11">
            <head>11. Reflection</head>
            <lg type="verse" n="11.1." xml:id="ref_vers1">
               <l>I find that I can see a light at the end down</l>
               <l>Beneath my self-indulgent pitiful hole.</l>
               <l>Defeated</l>
               <l>I Concede and move closer.</l>
               <l>I may find comfort here</l>
               <l>I may find peace within the emptiness.</l>
               <l>How pitiful.</l>
               <l>It's calling me.</l>
               <l>It's calling me.</l>
               <l>It's calling me.</l>
               <l>It's calling me.</l>
            </lg>
            <note corresp="#ref_vers1">Reflection is the second song of three indicated as connected
               by the artwork on the back of the sleeve for the album. It consists of the three
               tracks Disposition, Reflection, and Triad. This song references to the previous one.
               The protagonist finds himself/herself living in a psychological reality. His/her
               unconscious mind creates the illusion of an independed and isolated self. The quality
               of life process is that it wants to be limitless. Unable to break out of this
               isolated state of mind, the life force inherit in him/her calls the protagonist to
               his/her true nature.</note>
            <lg type="verse" n="11.2." xml:id="ref_vers2">
               <l>And in my darkest moment, fetal and weeping.</l>
               <l>The moon tells me a secret. My confidant.</l>
               <l>As full and bright as I am,</l>
               <l>this light is not my own</l>
               <l>A million light reflections pass over me</l>
               <l>It's source is bright and endless.</l>
               <l>She resuscitates the hopeless</l>
               <l>Without her we are lifeless satellites dreaming dreams.</l>
               <l>And as I pull my head out I am without one doubt</l>
               <l>Don't want to be down here feeding my narcissism</l>
               <l>I must crucify the ego before it's far too late</l>
               <l>I pray the light lifts me out</l>
            </lg>
            <note corresp="#ref_vers2">Hitting another rock bottom, the protagonist comes in direct
               contact with his/her life process/source/... and becoming aware of his/her constand
               need for preserving an illusional sense of self and in so becoming increasingly
               self-absorbed and narcistic.</note>
            <lg type="refrain" n="11.3." xml:id="ref_refrain1">
               <l>before I pine away.</l>
               <l>before I pine away.</l>
               <l>before I pine away.</l>
               <l>before I pine away.</l>
            </lg>
            <note corresp="#ref_refrain1">Pining means to lapse into a period of intense depression
               or melancholy due to one’s longing for or grief over someone or something. </note>
            <lg type="verse" n="11.4." xml:id="ref_vers3">
               <l>So crucify the ego before it's far too late</l>
               <l>To leave behind this place so negative and blind and cynical</l>
               <l>And you will come to find that we are all one mind</l>
               <l>Just let the light touch you and let the words spill thorough</l>
               <l>Just let them pass right through, bringing out our hope and reason.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg type="refrain" n="11.5." xml:id="ref_refrain2">
               <l>before I pine away.</l>
               <l>before I pine away.</l>
               <l>before I pine away.</l>
               <l>before I pine away.</l>
            </lg>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
